Robert G. Hoare papers, Inclusive: 1975-1994, undated, Bulk: 1983-1990.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Robert G. Hoare papers
Inclusive: 1975-1994, undated, Bulk: 1983-1990.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
69
Hoare, Robert "Bob" G., active 1975-1994
3 document boxes and 1 oversize box
The Robert G. Hoare Papers contain a variety of materials produced or collected by Robert G. Hoare, a Keston Institute contract researcher who monitored the religious situation in communist and post-communist Bulgaria.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
From approximately 1982 to the early 1990s, Robert G. “Bob” Hoare provided information to the Keston College research staff, specializing in the religious situation in Bulgaria. He prepared reports for KNS, RCL, and other publications, participated in Keston writing projects, and translated materials from Bulgarian and French.
Scope and Content
The Robert G. Hoare Papers cover the period from 1975 to 1994 with the bulk from 1983 to 1990. The materials focus on the religious situation in communist Bulgaria, including a brief period after the collapse of communism in the Eastern Bloc countries. The most notable topics include, but are not limited to, Bulgarian Armenians, persecution of Pastor Khristo Kulichev and Brother Dimiter of the Sofia Congregational Church, Bulgarian Orthodox Priest Fr. Hristo Subev, Varna Baptist Church, Christian literature for believers in Bulgaria, Islam and Muslims in Bulgaria, and Pentecostals in Bulgaria.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Robert Hoare Papers in untitled folders. Materials were organized into series according to their nature and topic and arranged chronologically.
The Robert G. Hoare Papers are organized into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Works, III. Subject Files, and IV. Collected Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 69.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Ignatov, Pavel; Kulichev, Khristo Khristov; Suămp;&bev, Khristofor; Zhivkov, Todor.
Subjects (Organizations)
Bŭlgarska pravoslavna t︠s︡ŭrkva.; Catholic Church -- Bulgaria -- History -- 20th century.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Bulgaria -- Church history -- 20th century.; Bulgaria -- Ethnic relations.
Subjects
Communism and Christianity -- Bulgaria.; Freedom of religion -- Bulgaria.; Human rights -- Bulgaria.; Liberty of conscience -- Bulgaria.; Muslims -- Soviet Union.; Pentecostalism -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Bulgaria.; Political prisoners -- Bulgaria.; Religion and state — Bulgaria.; Turks -- Bulgaria.
Genres
Articles.; Booklets.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Reports.
- Correspondence, 1985-1991; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains correspondence sent and received by Robert G. “Bob” Hoare while monitoring the situation of believers in Bulgaria for Keston College.
  The series is in good condition.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 69.
  - Correspondence: General, 1985 March-November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General, 1986 January-July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: General, 1986 August-November (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: General, 1987 January-February, 1988 October-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: General, 1989 January-March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 1989 April-July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: General, 1989 August-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: General, 1990 January-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: General, 1990 June-August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: General, 1990 September-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Translations, 1991 Janary-March (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Janice Broun: Father Blagoy Topuzliev, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: "Modern Martyrs" by Clare Best, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Ampleforth Conference, 1989 January-1990 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Bulgaria Embassy Press Release, 1986 October (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Literary Works, 1982-1991, undated; 2
  The largest series of the collection, Literary Works, includes correspondence, handwritten and typed notes, clippings, and draft manuscripts, produced and collected by Robert G. Hoare while working on articles, reports, translations, and information booklets on the religious situation in Bulgaria.
  - Bulgaria: Chronological Summary of Events: Bound Manuscript, 1987 March-1989 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (1 of 6), 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (2 of 6), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (3 of 6), 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (4 of 6), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (5 of 6), 1990 January-June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Items Submitted for KNS Nos. 214-372: Manuscripts, Clippings (6 of 6), 1990 July-1991 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reports: Bulgaria: Manuscripts, Clippings, Correspondence (1 of 2), 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reports: Bulgaria: Manuscripts, Clippings, Correspondence (2 of 2), 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - MARC Project: World Christianity: Eastern Europe: Correspondence, Manuscripts, Reports, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Contributions: Frontier: Manuscripts, Clippings, Correspondence, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Contributions: RTB, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - KNS Reports: Khristo Kulichev and Sofia Congregational Church: Clippings, Manuscripts, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - KNS Reports: Pavel Ignatov and Unregistered Pentecostal "Church of God": Clippings, Manuscripts, 1982-1983, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Comments: Religion in Communist Lands: Manuscripts, Clippings, Notes, 1983, 1986-1987, 1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paper: Sofia News: Political Parties and Factions: Manuscripts, Clippings, Notes, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Translations and Notes: Bulgaria: General: Manuscripts, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Translation: "Religiousness and Atheist Education in Our Country" by Krustiou Krustev ("Politicheska Prosveta," April 1987): Manuscript, Clippings (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Translations: Documents of Religious Rights Committee and Bulgarian Orthodox Church Holy Synod: Clippings, Manuscripts, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Translation: Keston College Information in French: Manuscripts, Clippings, 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts: Bulgaria: General, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript: Patriarch Maksim: Biographical Information, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: Todor Zhivkov: Biographical Information, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Comments: Article "Bulgarian Orthodox Church" by Melody Kusseff: Manuscripts, Notes, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Comments: Article "Church and State in Bulgaria" by Spas T. Raikin: Manuscripts, 1986 August 29 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Comments: Article "Successes and Failures of Atheism in Bulgaria" by Spas T. Raikin: Manuscripts, Notes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Project: Vatican and Eastern Europe: Correspondence, Manuscripts, Notes, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Booklet: Bulgaria: Basic Information for Keston College Use: Manuscript, 1991 March (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Information for Keston: Bulgaria: Manuscripts, Notes, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Subject Files, 1982-1991; 3
  The series includes newspaper clippings, manuscripts, print materials, and correspondence pertaining to Robert G. Hoare’s research interests.
  - Kulichev Brothers and Sofia Congregational Churches: Correspondence, Manuscripts, Notes, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pavel Ignatov and Unregistered Pentecostal "Church of God": Correspondence, Manuscripts, Notes, 1982-1983, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Father Khristofor Subev: Communications, Manuscripts, Notes, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Father Khristofor Subev: Documents, Communications, Images, Notes, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Father Krustu Stoianov Malinov: Clippings, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bulgaria: List of Needed Christian Literature, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Humanitarian Aid for Bulgaria: Clippings, Print Materials, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Computer Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Processing and Filing Instructions: Manuscripts, Notes, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Collected Materials, 1975-1994, undated; 4
  The series contains manuscripts, published reports, and print materials pertaining to religion and believers in Bulgaria collected by Robert G. Hoare for Keston College.
  - Abagar Bulgarian Catholic Literary Archive: Publications, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bulgarian Émigré Publications: Clippings, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bulgarian National Agrarian Union Publication: Svobodno Zemedelsko Zname, No. 21-22, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Bulgarian National Agrarian Union Publication: Svobodno Zemedelsko Zname, No. 31-32, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Bulgarian National Agrarian Union Publication: Svobodno Zemedelsko Zname, No. 33, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Bulgarian National Agrarian Union Publication: Svobodno Zemedelsko Zname, No. 35-36, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Janice Broun: Visit to Bulgaria: Reports, Documents, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Religion in Communist Lands Articles: Bulgaria: Manuscripts, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Bulgaria: General: Manuscripts, Clippings, 1975, 1985, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)